A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, 2007-2009 (bulk 2007)
Library of Virginia
- Series II. Files of TriData, a Division of System Planning Corporation, 2007., Extent: 5.78 cubic feet (17 boxes) and 1766 emails. (Box 5-21)
  - Series II. Files of TriData, Subseries C. Collected Documents Related to the Investigation, 2007., Extent: 3.85 cu. ft. (boxes 11-21) and 1766 emails
    - II.C.4. TriData, Files of Teresa Copping, 2007., Extent: 1.05 cu. ft. (boxes 19-21) and 208 emails
      - Drafts of Various Chapters of the Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Drafts of Various Chapters of the Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Drafts of Various Chapters of the Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Draft, Chapter III. Timeline of Events, with comments by Skadden, Arps, 8 August 2007 [RESTRICTED]. (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Draft, Chapter VI. Double Murder at West Amber Johnson Hall, 6 December 2007. (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - II.C.5. TriData, Files of Maria Argabright, July-August 2007., Extent: 29 emails
      The files of Maria Argabright, executive assistant, TriData, contain 29 emails sent and received between July and August 2007. Argabright's email is accessible online.
      Email subjects include: information compiled for the report (list of interviews, photographs).
      Email correspondents include: Phil Schaenman and Hollis Stambaugh.
    - II.C.6. TriData, Files of Shania Flagg, April-August 2007., Extent: 87 emails
      The files of Shania Flagg, TriData, contain 87 emails sent and received between April and August 2007. Flagg's email is accessible online.
      Email subjects include: Panel correspondence and Virginia Tech Panel website.
      Email correspondents include: Ben Huson, Gerald Massengill and Hollis Stambaugh.
- Series III. Files of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP, 2007., Extent: 6.83 cubic feet (21 boxes) and 2166 emails. (Box 22-39)
  The Files of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP series documents the legal advice provided to the Virginia Tech Review Panel and TriData as well as the firm's comments and edits of the Panel's report to Governor Kaine. Series is arranged into eight subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. General Files; Subseries B. Files of Bradley Marcus; Subseries C. Files of Ian Erickson; Subseries D. Files of Mike Kelly; Subseries E. Files of Michael Tierney; Subseries F. Files of Amy Sabrin; Subseries G. Files of Rich Brusca; and Subseries H. Files of Anne Kim. This series includes health records, legal advice, and personal information that are restricted for 75 years by the Code of Virginia (Virginia Government Data Collection and Dissemination Practices Act, Virginia Public Records Act, Virginia Health Records Privacy Act). The majority of this series is restricted (attorney-client privilege and/or attorney work product).
  On 29 May 2007, The Virginia Tech Review Panel engaged the international law firm of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP to provide legal advice to the Panel on a pro bono basis. Governor Tim Kaine, in consultation with Attorney General Robert McDonnell, agreed to retain outside counsel for the Panel in order to avoid any potential conflict of interest. Litigation partners Richard Brusca and Amy Sabrin were the two lead attorneys for the Panel with assistance from other partners and lawyers in Skadden's Washington, D.C. office.
  Skadden provided legal advice on a variety of subjects: record keeping under the Virginia Public Records Act and Virginia Data Collection and Dissemination Practices Act; Public access to meetings and documents under the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (FOIA); Clery Act; and information on privacy laws (law enforcement records, court records, medical information and records, and education records).
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries A. General Files, April-October 2007., Extent: 1.40 cu. ft. (boxes 22-25)
    This subseries contains correspondence, news articles, and legal documents. This subseries includes legal advice that is restricted for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78.
    - III.A.1. Correspondence, May-September 2007
      Arranged chronologically, the correspondence consists of printouts of emails and attachments sent and received by Skadden staff members. Also included are memorandums and legal opinions. These records contain attorney-client communications and attorney work products and are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Box 22 is restricted.
      - 30 May 2007 - 12 June 2007 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - 13 June 2007 - 15 June 2007 (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - 16 June 2007 - 21 June 2007 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - 22 June 2007 - 27 June 2007 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - 28 June 2007 - 13 July 2007 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - 14 July 2007 - 18 September 2007 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - III.A.2. News Articles, April-October 2007
      Records consist of printouts of news articles related to the Virginia Tech shooting and the work of the Panel. Box 23 is unrestricted.
      - 18 April 2007 - 14 June 2007 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - 15 June 2007 - 27 June 2007 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - 28 June 2007 - 17 July 2007 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - 18 July 2007 - 7 August 2007 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - 8 August 2007 - 23 August 2007 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - 24 August 2007 - 15 October 2007 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - III.A.3. Records, 2007
      The majority of this material contains attorney-client communications and attorney work products and is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. For box 24, restricted documents have been sealed but have not been removed from the collection. Box 25 is restricted.
      - Key Documents, June-July 2007 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Executive Order creating the Panel, June 2007 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Fatal School Shootings in the United States, 1996-2007 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Initial Statutes for Research (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Panel Meeting Presentations, 11 June 2007 (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - Drafts of the Review Panel Report by Chapter (I-V) (Box 24, Folder 6)
      - Drafts of the Review Panel Report by Chapter (VI-XI) (Box 24, Folder 7)
      - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007 (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - Case Team Documents from the System under 813000/0189 [RESTRICTED] (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - Case Team Documents from the System under 813000/0189 [RESTRICTED] (Box 25, Folder 2)
      - Case Team Documents from the System under 813000/0189 [RESTRICTED] (Box 25, Folder 3)
      - Case Team Documents from the System (in suspense - 888888/6015 [RESTRICTED] (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Case Team Documents from the System (in suspense - 888888/6015 [RESTRICTED] (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries B. Bradley Marcus, 2007., Extent: 0.70 cu. ft. (boxes 26-27) and 410 emails
    This subseries documents the work that Skadden attorney Bradley Marcus did for the Panel. Included are working papers, notes, legal advice, and email. This subseries contains attorney-client communications and attorney work product and is restricted (boxes 26 and 27) from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78.
    Marcus sent and received 410 emails between May and September 2007. There are 188 confidential emails that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Marcus's unrestricted email is accessible online.
    Email subjects include: news updates and legal research conducted for Panel.
    Notable email includes: email thread by Panel members, dated 24-25 June 2007, detailing the need for the Panel to meet privately and exchange information and views.
    Email correspondents include: Richard Brusca, Ian Erickson, Anne Kim, Tannia Nazelrod, Lauren Regan, Larry Roberts, Amy Sabrin, Hollis Stambaugh and Michael Tierney.
    - Bradley Marcus's Working Files and Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Bradley Marcus's Working Files and Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Bradley Marcus's Working Files and Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Bradley Marcus's Working Files and Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Bradley Marcus's Working Files and Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Bradley Marcus's Working Files and Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Bradley Marcus's Working Files and Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Preliminary Legal Advice to the Virginia Tech Review Panel, 2007. (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Preliminary Legal Advice to the Virginia Tech Review Panel, 2007. (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries C. Ian Erickson, 2007., Extent: 0.53 cu. ft. (boxes 27-28) and 364 emails
    This subseries documents the work of Skadden attorney Ian Erickson did for the Panel. Included are memorandums, legal advice, and email. This subseries contains attorney-client communications and attorney work product and is restricted (boxes 27 and 28) from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78.
    Erickson sent and received 364 emails between May and August 2007. There are 164 confidential emails that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Erickson's unrestricted email is accessible online.
    Notable email includes: email from Diane Strickland, dated 19 June 2007, to Amy Sabrin documenting problems getting Cho's records from Cook Counsel Center; email from Any Sabrin, dated 23 August 2007, to Panel members and staff detailing her comments on the Executive Summary of the Panel report; and email thread by Panel members, dated 24-25 June 2007, detailing the need for the Panel to meet privately and exchange information and views.
    Email correspondents include: Richard Brusca, Jim Kudla, Bradley Marcus, Larry Roberts, Amy Sabrin, Phil Schaenman, Hollis Stambaugh and Michael Tierney.
    - Laws and Regulations (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Laws and Regulations (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Cases (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Memos (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Memos (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Memos (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Tech Facts (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries D. Mike Kelly, 2007., Extent: 0.35 cu. ft. (box 29)
    This subseries documents the work of Skadden attorney Mike Kelly did for the Panel. Included are correspondence, newspaper articles and legal advice. This subseries contains attorney-client communications and attorney work product and is restricted (box 29) from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78.
    - Correspondence/Emails, June 2007. (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Panel Contact List, May 2007. (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - 2006 Executive Orders (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Articles, April 2007. (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, June 2007. (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Research (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries E. Michael Tierney, 2007., Extent: 0.53 cu. ft. (boxes 29-30) and 485 emails
    This subseries documents the work of Skadden attorney Michael Tierney did for the Panel. Included are handwritten meeting and telephone call notes, memorandums, and email. This subseries contains attorney-client communications and attorney work product and is restricted (boxes 29-30) from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78.
    Tierney sent and received 485 emails between May and September 2007. There are 67 confidential emails that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Tierney's unrestricted email is available online.
    Email subjects include: news updates; legal research conducted for panel; comments on chapter drafts; and collection of Panel records.
    Notable email includes: email thread by Panel members and staff, dated 17 August 2007, discussing the status of report and the need for more time; email from Amy Sabrin, dated 14 August 2007, to Skadden attorneys forwarding email from Wendell Flinchum addressing the Virginia Tech police department's authority to disseminate warnings.
    Email correspondents include: Richard Brusca, Gordon Davies, Anne Kim, Jim Kudla, Marcus Martin, Gerald Massengill, Lauren Regan, Amy Sabrin, Phil Schaenman, Bela Sood, Hollis Stambaugh and Diane Strickland.
    - Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Attorney Notes, 2007. (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Preliminary Legal Advice to Virginia Tech Review Panel, presented by Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP, 2007. (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Privacy Presentation/Report Section, 2007. (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Commitment Hearing Project, June 2007. (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - FOIA Cases and Advisory Opinions, 2007. (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Government Data Collection and Dissemination Practices, 2007. (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - FOIA, 2007. (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Initial Media Coverage, 2007. (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Deliberative Process, 2007. (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Virginia Tech Review Panel, Closed Meeting Agenda, 19 July 2007. (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Draft of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Preliminary Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, 15 August 2007 (Tierney copy). (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries F. Amy Sabrin, 2007., Extent: 0.70 cu. ft. (boxes 31-32) and 798 emails
    This subseries documents the work of Skadden attorney Amy Sabrin did for the Panel. Included are correspondence, memorandums, chapter drafts of Panel report, and email. This subseries contains attorney-client communications and attorney work product and is restricted (boxes 31-32) from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78.
    Sabrin sent and received 798 emails between July and October 2007. There are 122 confidential emails that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Sabrin's unrestricted email is accessible online.
    Subjects include: contacting Cho's family; engagement of Skadden as counsel for the Panel; news articles; legal research conducted for Panel; comments on chapter drafts; collection of Panel records; writing of report; and Panel meetings.
    Notable email includes: email thread dated 29-30 August 2007 on the leak of the final report to the New York Times and the Governor's Office decision to post it online; email thread between Roger Depue and Bela Sood, dated 22-23 August 2007, detailing their differences of opinion about Cho's mental health; email from Bela Sood, dated 10 August 2007, to Panel expressing her concerns about the final review draft of the report and requesting a delay in release of report to 30 August; email from Michael Tierney, dated 29 June 2007, to Richard Brusca and Amy Sabrin, containing notes of telephone conversation with Roanoke Firearms related to Cho's purchase of 9mm Glock 19; email from Diane Strickland, dated 19 June 2007, to Amy Sabrin documenting problems getting Cho's records from Cook Counsel Center; email from Any Sabrin, dated 23 August 2007, to Panel members and staff detailing her comments on the Executive Summary of the Panel report; email thread between Panel members, dated 15 August 2007, on gun control; and email thread between Panel members, staff, and attorneys, dated 27 June 2007, on the need to meet to discuss various issues.
    Correspondents include: Richard Brusca, Gordon Davies, Roger Depue, Carroll Ann Ellis, Ian Erickson, Anne Kim, Jim Kudla, Bradley Marcus, Marcus Martin, Gerald Massengill, Lauren Regan, Larry Roberts, Phil Schaenman, Wade Smith, Bela Sood, Hollis Stambaugh, Diane Strickland and Michael Tierney.
    - Clery Act, 2007. (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Clery Act, 2007. (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, June-August 2007. (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Draft Report Sections, Chapter II. University Setting and Security, 7 August 2007. (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Draft Report Sections, Chapter III. Timeline of Events, 8 August 2007. (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Guns, June 2007. (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Fatal School Shootings in the United States, 1966-2007. (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Panel Member Liability, 2007. (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Panel Member Liability, 2007. (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Panel Member Liability, 2007. (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda, June-July 2007. (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Preliminary Legal Advice to Virginia Tech Review Panel, presented by Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher and Flom LLP, 2007. (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007 (Final Report). (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Statutes, 2007. (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Series III. Files of Skadden, Subseries G. Rich Brusca, 2007., Extent: 3.33 cu. ft. (boxes 33-39)
    This subseries documents the work of Skadden attorney Rich Brusca did for the Panel. Included are correspondence, legal advice, memorandums, meeting materials, news articles, chapter drafts of Panel report, and email (printed). The majority of this series is restricted (attorney-client privilege and/or attorney work product). Boxes, 36, 36A, 38 and 39 are restricted. Boxes 34 and 37 are unrestricted. Boxes 33, 35, 35A, 35B are open; restricted documents have been sealed but have not been removed from the box.
    Notable documents include: Virginia Tech Review Panel Report, Tentative Outline, indicating proposed authors for each section of report, 25 June 2007 (b33, f8); printed email between Panel members, TriData, Skadden, and the governor's office, 25 May to 11 September 2007 (b35, f2 to b35A). Email includes discussions about draft chapters of report and release of report.
    - Review Panel Contact List (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - New Memorandum Information/Blackbook Entries (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Tech Review Panel letterhead (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Interview Table (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Skadden Invoices (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Fatal School Shootings in US (1996-2007) (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Summary of Information Privacy Law Prepared for the Virginia Tech Panel (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Tech Review Panel Report - Tentative Outline (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - FOIA Requirements for Closed Meeting 25 June 2007. (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Records Request to Virginia Tech from the Virginia Tech Review Panel, 21 June 2007. (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - Filing - Order: Release of Audio Recording of Commitment Hearing of Seung-Hui Cho, 18 June 2007. (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - Filing - Motion for Appropriate Relief, 18 June 2007. (Box 33, Folder 12)
    - Background Information on Executive Orders in VA, 30 May 2007. (Box 33, Folder 13)
    - Cho Temporary Detention Order, 13 December 2005. (Box 33, Folder 14)
    - August 20 Meeting Materials - Summary of Talking Points for Announcing a Closed Session, 20 August 2007. (Box 33, Folder 15)
    - July 19 Panel Meeting Materials (Box 33, Folder 16)
    - July 18 Panel Meeting Materials (Box 33, Folder 17)
    - Virginia Tech Panel Meeting Materials (May 21/June 6) (Box 33, Folder 18)
    - Governor Meeting Materials (May 21, 2007) (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - General Correspondence (Generated Outside of Skadden Offices) (Box 33, Folder 20)
    - Notes: Mass Fatalities - Homicides at Virginia Tech (Box 33, Folder 21)
    - Signed Authorizations from Cho Family, 27 June 2007. (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - Letter to Cho Family Asking for Authorization to View Confidential Records, 21 June 2007. (Box 33, Folder 23)
    - Executive Order 53 (2007) Virginia Tech Review Panel (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - Skadden Engagement Letter, 1 June 2007. (Box 33, Folder 25)
    - Letter to Ms. Melanie Baise re: FERPA and State Laws re: Mandatory Reporting Requirements (Box 33, Folder 26)
    - Newspaper Articles, 14 September 2007 - 31 August 2007. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper Articles, 30 August 2007 - 29 August 2007. (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper Articles, 28 August 2007 - 10 August 2007. (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Articles, 10 August 2007 - 3 July 2007. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Articles, 2 July 2007 - 22 June 2007. (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper Articles, 21 June 2007 - 5 June 2007. (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Emails, 30 August 2007 - 11 September 2007. (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Emails, 24 August 2007 - 29 August 2007. (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Emails, 23 August 2007 - 16 August 2007. (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Emails, 15 August 2007 - 10 August 2007. (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Emails, 9 August 2007 - 1 August 2007. (Box 35A, Folder 1)
    - Emails, 31 July 2007 - 22 July 2007. (Box 35A, Folder 2)
    - Emails, 20 July 2007 - 28 June 2007. (Box 35A, Folder 3)
    - Emails, 27 June 2007 - 20 June 2007. (Box 35A, Folder 4)
    - Emails, 19 June 2007 - 7 June 2007. (Box 35B, Folder 1)
    - Emails, 6 June 2007 - 25 May 2007. (Box 35B, Folder 2)
    - Emails, 12 September 2007 - 8 October 2007. (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Crisis of Leadership: A Response to the Virginia Tech Panel Report by Vincent Bove, October 2007. (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - FOIA Research (part one) (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - FOIA Research (part two) (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Summary of the HIPAA Privacy Rule (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Legal Advice to Virginia Tech Panel by Skadden (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - A Guide for High School Students: Transition of Students with Disabilities to Postsecondary Education, March 2007. (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Crime Commission Report (HJR Final Report: Study on Campus Safety, HD 36, 2006) (part one) (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Crime Commission Report (HJR Final Report: Study on Campus Safety, HD 36, 2006) (part two) (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Preliminary Legal Advice to Virginia Tech Panel by Skadden (copy 1) (Box 36A, Folder 1)
    - Preliminary Legal Advice to Virginia Tech Panel by Skadden (copy 2) (Box 36A, Folder 2)
    - Preliminary Legal Advice to Virginia Tech Panel by Skadden (copy 3) (Box 36A, Folder 3)
    - Preliminary Legal Advice to Virginia Tech Panel by Skadden (copy 4) (Box 36A, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Documents [records from other parts of the collection filed with Brusca's material] (Box 36A, Folder 5)
    - The Handbook for Campus Crime Reporting (2005) (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Public Records Management Manual (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Materials from the National Center for Victims of Crime with video tapes (part one) (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Materials from the National Center for Victims of Crime with video tapes (part two) (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Final Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel Given to the Governor (August 2007) (File 1) (part one) (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Final Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel Given to the Governor (August 2007) (File 1) (part two) (Box 38, Folder 1)